hi welcome back to lum rim
and
i have a friend from shenzhen he told me
i counted the seven wrong it's true
okay the first one is equanimity we
don't count it among the seven
and then uh marche which means
recognizing all beings have been your
mom
remember all the nice things they did
for you when they were your mom
chin so
try to pay them back
[Music]
sorrow for their troubles
compassion
and then i forgot to mention
which is
to take personal responsibility to take
care of them
so i forgot to mention that one and then
we're on number seven now
which is the result of the first seven
makes sense
no it doesn't
yeah okay so it's really six and a half
before that and we're on seven okay all
right here we go sam keaney
uh they thought
and i like to go through the tibetan on
the loan room
my teacher went through it three times
and it helped me a lot uh again
i do believe this is the greatest book
ever written in tibetan language so as a
you know a lot of the classics
that we study in the mixed nuts for
example they are translations
of sanskrit they were not written in
tibetan
so
and
and also the the sastras the ancient
commentaries so we have 990
sutras in tantras written in sanskrit
we have uh 3
shastras from india commentaries
and
then then then the tibetan tradition
starts
after 4 600
books
then starts the tibetan tradition which
is roughly about 300 000 books it's the
largest scriptural tradition in the
world and uh
that's why we're trying to
catalog them all and input them all and
save them all so that would take another
500 years or something okay
we finished 35 years we finished 16
million pages it's online for free
but we still have a long way to go okay
so
if you want to learn
uh tibetan language
and therefore open your mind to 300 000
spiritual classes
then this is the book to do it so i'm
i'm gonna keep
mentioning the tibetan words it will
plant a seed in your mind
three lifetimes from now you'll take an
interest in it
okay
all right
dumbass i'm kenny so uh
here's the
we have reached
the seventh of the seven step
advices okay
cooler uh
core
core means a heavy load
okay court means a heavy load
care means to carry it okay
means to carry a heavy load
what's the word in sanskrit for a wife
which probably came into berta
okay i'm sorry bertha
uh
but it means burden comes from the same
room it means uh in the ancient times
in the less enlightened times
the boy was carrying the lady okay
uh so there's your
okay
now
he says this person says
you can almost guess it means i'm not
sure i could do that
i ate you means
you know now that i understand
everything involved
with planet jumping like
i don't know
i i think it's a little bit out of my
skill set
you know
yeah i'm not sure i can handle that you
know and if
[Music]
come on stanley 100 bucks
99.98
[Music]
that's a closer guess
but i'm happy at least he's trying
uh
to to do the
to take care of one living being
yeah i can't even take care of one
person
you know here's a picture for you guys
okay
like
i you want me to take care of all living
beings i can't guard them take care of
myself you know
you know maybe two to be impossible
one is hard for me you know i can't i
can hardly
take care of myself
and you want me to take care of every
little me i mean come on it's kind of
joke right
you know and it's very funny and it's so
true right like god i can't even pay my
own bills
you want me to take everybody else's
bills you know you must be crazy
you know it's like
i i truly
have trouble taking care of myself
and and i don't
really i mean it sounds nice
and i think it would be very noble
to take care of everybody
but
to be honest
i have days when i can't take care of
myself you know so i i don't know about
this thing
uh
then john duncan
can
she tell by the way this is the
definition of local right bench nipper
to be able to do a function
it's the it's the technical definition
in in logic
for a functioning thing
it's able to perform a function
so
uh
cell means
what's chock cell
chakra cell means prostrate but what's
it literally mean
shock means hand
cell means to look for something
and it means to the word in
tibetan for prostrating
means to
to
look for
a gift from the hand of your llama
look tell me to search for
chalk means hand honorific
chucks the word it's interesting the
word for frustration in tibetan means to
seek
something nice from the hand of your
teacher
okay so here we have cell
uh
cell here means is there a duncan nuba
is there someone
is there anybody who has that ability
okay like
i'm open to the idea of trying to
develop that ability
i right now to be honest i can't even
take care of one person
but
i'm open to the possibility
if you can show me one person who can do
it
you know i can try to figure out how
they're doing that you know so show me
one person sell means
sh you know
i'm looking for one person who can do it
okay
and then i'll
i'll try to copy you down
i'll try to copy them okay so
here's what the sentence says
you know yeah okay take care all the
meanings right
i can't take care of myself
but if you can show me
show me somebody who can do it then you
know i'll i'll meet them i'll talk to
them maybe i can learn i'm open to
learning just show me someone who can do
that okay
uh
then it says
well uh
let's just take those really super
capable people in the world okay
let's take those
really strong people
in this world you can find people who
are really strong
in this life
there are people
like i don't know famous politicians
or
famous
elon musk
there are people
special people tough people
great people
let's take their example
you know and then here's a picture of
them
okay
this picture has more meaning than your
guess
okay what what's the deeper meaning of
this picture
yeah in the end they are just dead meat
okay
all these elon musks
all these uh super powerful politicians
in yeah they look strong but in the end
they're just dead meat
okay same as you and me not much
difference okay
they can lift a little more stuff they
can run a little faster
they can collect more money
they can
attack another country
and in the end they're just dead meat
they're all the same you know so that's
what he says in mexico
take those big people
they are also helpless
they are also cannot even take care of
themselves okay these big politicians
these big power guys
uh these big business people
these wealthy guys
you know he's considering a possibility
and he's rejecting it
and i said well how about
how about this big you know
war guys this big powerful guy's nuclear
power
you know they must be powerful you know
and they're like yeah
they're just dead meat they're just skin
hanging on dead knee you know they're
the same as us
they don't have any more power than you
have
you know you can't even have a good day
for yourself then
guess what neither can they
okay
all the power they seem to have they
there's nothing there
they're just
they're just me waiting to die
you know same as us they're the same as
them so it's funny you know bubble
grimaces well yeah okay i'll show you
somebody who can take care of lots of
people these guys
and then pabonka in his own sentence he
says nah
they're just telling me too
they're just gonna end up in some
garbage pile like like everybody else
and they will be forgotten quickly by
the way
there's there's nothing more frustrating
in translating the ancient
books
then trying to keep track of dead kings
and
you know
that the sentence is always the same the
most powerful guy
of boogadoo you know
and you're like
he's dead he's got booga doogoos dead
and gone you know where the hell is
boogadoo
and then it takes like a year to find
this
vast kingdom of boogadoo you know
and the kingdom's gone the city's gone
the city's buried on 120 feet of dirt
travesty
where buddha taught the diamond cutter
finally they found it not long ago i
went there
it's 120 feet down
it shavasti means the biggest city
around you know
famous
by charlie these famous cities new york
paris
moscow
you know they're all
they're going to read them in a book and
say what's paris
what's what's new york you know and
they're going to say oh you know some
kind of
ruins
you can find him uh you know you go dig
under the new atlantic coastline
and
you can find this manhattan
it'll always be like that okay so he's
like
okay
you know our hearts are pretty powerful
guys
you know definition in our heart
roughly
yeah what sega
yeah they have stopped their negative
emotion
forever
i always think of it in terms of my
little brother
my we had i had four we were four
brothers in my family
and uh we were divided into we call the
big guys and the little guys
and the big guys slept on two bunk beds
and the little guys slept in another
mountain so we kind of had this division
between the big guys and the little guys
and the mission
of the two little guys was to irritate
the two big guys
so and they actually would say in the
morning i'm gonna make you mad today
you know i will piss you off today and
you're like nah you can't piss me off
you know i
now that you've warned me
you can't piss me off they could always
do it you know
and uh by the end of the day you're like
you know and they said they would
actually laugh at us the little guys
would laugh at the big guy
[Music]
we did it we got you upset again you
know i'm like dang you know
and i always thought the definition of
an arhat
is a big guy who can't be pissed off by
a little guy okay
the person who can no longer be made
upset
is the definition of an aha okay
[Music]
it doesn't really help other people they
also die
they also die
being in my heart doesn't change this
human body
they're also dead
they reach nirvana
but it's not enough to be of a real help
to other people it's not enough okay
let me know
they can't really help people that much
okay they can teach them how to not get
upset at the little guys
but they can't teach them how not to die
they don't know that yet they haven't
got there yet okay
so even
even nirvana okay not enough not enough
to be able to help other people
ok
[Music]
um
and then pablo invented starts going up
the ladder
of spiritual achievement right so what's
next
after our hut
dumbo
uh bodhisattva on the first place up a
level 10 body cell phone level
so on the day that you see the emptiness
directly
uh you reach a level called goa and
and and and by definition
when you reach that level you also have
bodhichitta so you achieve direct
perception emptiness and you achieve
bodhichitta you're on the first body
suffering level of 10
of 10 levels okay
can they help people
he says
yeah maybe they could do some good stuff
get what she took john simki
but compared to
keva chitok
and that's a new word for you guys i
think tim never thought
uh
cheek talk means uh one life to go
a body suffer with one life to go before
they become enlightened okay
so that's called
the person who just reached the first of
the ten bodhisattva novels
compared to the person who's
like on 9.9 or something
uh
they can't they're not really that
helpful i'd rather find a 99.9 guy
than the guy who just saw him in this
okay
all right uh so he's going up through
the ladder
[Music]
people who just saw emptiness yeah they
can help you a lot
but compared to people who are half an
hour from becoming buddha
i'll
[Music]
what's next
one life to go is there anybody between
this is cute he says though
well try to imagine a guy who's in his
final
his or her final life
as a bodhisattva okay they're they're
going to be a buddha in this life
and they are changing
this is one of the twelve
features of a true monk
or none
they make their home
[Music]
at the base of a tree a real monk a real
nun
the reason they have this cute shawl
is that's a sleeping bag
they wear a sleeping bag nowadays it's
all ceremonial and it's a big mess
you get caught without your shawl you
get beat by the debate master
you get caught folding your shell the
wrong way you get beat by the debate
master no one in the whole monastery has
ever used their shawl
as a sleeping bag
but that's what they were for
that's what the shawl is for okay and
so in the ancient times
if you stayed in a monastery you were
breaking your vows
if you stayed in a in a covered
enclosure you were breaking your nose
you're supposed to sleep under a tree
in your sleeping bag
that's why roll wall schultz were so
popular
uh
okay and we're gonna talk about wool
shells by the way
uh anyway
why does it come here
he's chunk
tree right what's chang
yeah i already sat down under the
body tree
already sat down by the time they stand
up they will be a buddha
okay they already sat down you know we
were you there did you go to
we went about gaia
i translate the damn car situated the
first time i ever thought it was sitting
there where the buddha said that's the
first time i taught the diamond cutter
in england
we went to bogaya and i sat
i put my bottom down where the buddha
put his bottom down and the bodhi tree
was over my head and uh and i taught the
diamond cutter so now he says
well you got this kind of bodhisattva
who's got one life to go but how does
how does their ability to help you
compare to the ability
of the guy who just sat down
and by the time he stands up he'll be a
buddha he or she would be a buddha
are they useful
he says not really
i mean they
they also didn't cross that line yet
okay they cannot take care of countless
beings
they are sitting down they are putting
their bottom
down
in front of the bodhi tree
uh
but they're not there yet they didn't
cross that line yet to where they can
take care of everybody at the same time
they're still putting one bottom down on
one tree
okay so it's beautiful how he goes up to
the
you know first he starts with us guys at
the office
you know like i can't even have a good
day don't ask me to take care of living
being well how about this big muscular
you know elon musk and these other
politicians
wow they're just dead meat too you know
well how about our hawks yeah great our
hearts you know
they they disappearing about the great
what it should do for me
and then well how about these
bodhisattvas are just scientists yeah
you're getting there they're pretty good
but they don't compare to those guys
here in their final lifetime
yeah well how about those guys not i
mean among all the guys in their final
lifetime i'd rather be the guy who's
putting his butt down in front of the
buddha tree and he's in half an hour
it's going to be a buddha
yeah but is he really helpful
i'll take a full buddha you know i'll
have what she's having
[Music]
i'll take bruno okay
is an idiom which means matchless
you cannot find uh
anything better out of that whole list
of cool people
i'll take the full buddha the guy after
he stands up
uh after putting his bottom down at the
booty bunny tree
and then he says here's your picture
this is how you're going to remember
if you compare the
square footage of the universe
to the space in this guy's palm
that's the difference
okay a person who has become enlightened
who has stood up from the bodhi tree
you compare their ability to take care
of people it's equal
to the length and breadth of the
universe
and compared to the compared to this
much space
this much space is everybody else even
in our heart even uh
even someone who's emptiness directly
even a person who's in their last life
even a person who's sitting down at the
body tree
and they have half an hour to go
all of their ability to help people is
this much
and then as soon as you cross that line
under the bodhi tree and you become a
full buddha
then
then your capacity is equal to
the universe
the endless universe your capacity
matches
the square footage of the endless number
and that's the difference he says go for
that one
don't settle for left you know come on
nirvana are ya i go for go for the go
for the big one
because your abilities are billions and
it's countless
there's no measurement of how much
people you can help okay there's no
measurement
uh
and here's an important uh
description
of a of a buddhist of capacity
and they say
say shendon
so it's a common uh
tibetan personal name plunder
geshe
supa's first name was thunderbite ellie
in wisconsin great geshe
uh sunda
sunda means
[Music]
it's the capacity to show up
at the moment you're needed
without premeditation
okay so someone
gets a flat tire in texas canyon and
you're there
you know texas canyon it's where all
those boulders are on the way here from
tucson
that that little hill where there's all
these weird boulders
it's a great place to have a flood tire
there's all these uh 18 wheelers and
there's no place to pull off
if you ever have a flat tire it's gonna
be there
uh
sunder means uh
you just show up you're the next car
you're in the next car you're always in
the next car
okay someone breaks down
they're changing their tire
you're always in the next car you stop
and you help them
nest
chew
her her car went off the road there she
fell off a cliff
her car went off a cliff there on the
way back one night after class
and no one saw her
and her she just disappeared
and these two uh guys from mexico were
driving by and they said hey and
somebody's down there and they stopped
and they took care of her so
that's slynder that means you show up at
the right time in the right place total
syndrome
everywhere in the universe when someone
needs you you're boom you're there
that would be better right
like that's slender okay so try to
imagine
syndrome
now what if people what if somebody
breaks down at texas canyon and somebody
breaks down outside of buoy which is
worse
you know
then you're both places at the same time
that's linda okay they break down down
here
at midnight i've done that before
and uh you you're broken down out here
in midnight
and your friend is at texas canyon just
had a flat tire and hundred means you
show up at both places at the same
moment okay
and then how many others
no number no number that would be cool
that would be nice
okay
that's bodhichitta okay
means
may i be the
universe's tire fixer
you know and i just show up
i'm always in the next car
and i always stop for you
and i fix your i fix your tire no matter
where you are
that that's something that's really cool
that's the difference between the space
in your palm and the space in the whole
universe like this is fixing one
person's tire
and that's fixing everybody's tire at
the same moment okay
in the whole universe and that
that's not a bad example that's actually
correct
okay all the flat tires in the whole
universe you are facing at the same time
that's something
and and you have to think like that when
you think about
because you are
limited right now to one physical body
you naturally believe that you could
only help one person at one time
and you have to get over that limitation
you have to stop thinking like that okay
stop thinking
that i wish i could help somebody you
know you got to think
could i automatically help everybody at
the same time
in in different bodies and that that's
sexy that's something okay so try to
imagine it just try to imagine it and
then that will help you reach that state
of mind right i'd like to fix all the
pirates
at the same time
i'd like to sweep out all the cabins in
the damn mountain at the same time
by the way i don't know who cleaned my
camera but it's really nice and i
appreciated them
i know what it is to clean the cabin
i'm sure they were done one by one
it's a beautiful the place looks very
beautiful
so thank you you're blessed with
special people
okay sange
only the buddha is the universal
tire fixer okay
all right
copa
back in the teachings on going for
refuge
we talked about how much the buddha can
help you when you go from refuge so now
he says reverse that teaching what's
that mean
you're not you thinking about how much
the buddhists can help you you are
the buddha is saying yeah that's me oh
that's a nice description
that's who i am yeah so he said if you
want to have some fun
go back to the refuge teaching
and look at it from the point of view of
the person they're talking about
not from the point of view of the person
who needs help
you know but you know saying
you know i think
now you're the buddha that they're
talking to
now now think about how cool you are
he says you might want to go back there
and look up all those cool things
that buddha's supposed to do for you
when you got in trouble
and now think of being being that person
okay
so guess what grandpa did
i went back and got you that list
okay
so
i think when you teach you should
prepare
in a leisurely way
like the whole drive you got to get
ellie to drive you around so you can
prepare in the car that's the story of
my life
and
you should
when they say think back you should go
back okay if you're gonna be a real
teacher you should
take the time
to to go back and find okay so we're
gonna go i actually not only went back i
got you pictures
all right uh
here's the first one tim
yeah i i
this is called uh long jig
you are beyond all fear yourself you are
beyond all fear
yourself first quality of refuge
now you are the refuge of them right so
before it was
hey take refuge in the buddha they are
beyond all fear now it's hey take refuge
in me i'm beyond the fear okay and this
guy's
you ever stood on places like that like
you're gonna be the first person to walk
out there and the rock falls off
and
yeah i always think that i never get on
those rocks i always stand back
i'll be the first one
where the rock falls off you know
okay so
totally beyond all fear nothing to fear
imagine right
not even death
nothing fearless okay you will be okay
you will be
you will be done
that's that's bodhichitta now instead of
refuge
which is taken by wimps
now your buddy tina now you're like i'm
the one
you know i i'm not afraid of anything i
can help you i can help you i can fix
your tire okay
that's the first one okay second one tim
[Music]
shen uh
tanzania do it top k
tim for 10 cents
okay 12 cents
14.
yeah skillful meats right help keeper
skill for me
uh why are we showing this guy
uh
i like the word agile
i like the word agile agile means uh
you know
can do special stuff when it's necessary
think uh agile you know they're like
we got a problem here you're like
i got it i got that i got the that's uh
cupcake buddhists are super mentally
agile problem solvers okay that's what
uh
to do what
shenzhen
duo to free all other beings from
fear
they are super creative
you know super computer creative their
mind is like a super computer
and if someone has a problem they're
like
okay i got it
you know so that's the second quality of
a buddha special figure
router of
solutions for
people who are screwed up
i got it i got just the thing for you
i'll take care of everything i'll take
care of everything isn't that nice to be
able to say that
i i love that like it doesn't happen
very often but
somebody's like i got a problem and
you're like huh
i got it covered i gotta come in
uh don't worry i i got
it okay
somebody comes to you you just made
six hundred thousand dollars this week
somebody says can you loan me 200 bucks
you know
i got it covered
chill out
i got it all coming so that's the second
quality of a buddha i i got it covered
super
agile
problem solving top cable top keppa
means
super agile mental problem solver
for anything people need you're like
i got it i got it
i know you should do
they save you from all your
problems okay
all right third we got four by the way
here's the third one
um
[Music]
you have a wag for everybody
that's definition of a buddha
you know
i have a dog i mean my wife's
son
has a dog like that he's got a wag for
everyone
you can kick him you can spit on him you
can yell at him and he's like
so
i call it a wack family could not tiptoe
equal
compassion and love for all loving
beings
[Music]
overlook the differences
german cognate algon
english cognate i
look overlook the differences okay
anyway nearing chart fung means
i'm incapable of treating some people as
closer and some people as a father
i'm not capable of saying i'll take care
of you but i won't take care of you know
that's the third quality of the buddha
okay so
equal wags
for everybody
probably lick also
they don't have
favorites they don't play favorites okay
if you're a living being
you get a wag
and a lick you know
and there's dogs like that right you try
to kick him and they're like licking you
you know
and uh
so the buddha has this quality of uh
equal affection
towards every other living being and
there's dogs like that right you haven't
met dogs
yeah you try to kick him and they're
like licking your foot you know
[Music]
okay equal wag
um
[Music]
how many we got qualities
four so we've got one more right
all right
uh
the waitress who treats all diners the
same regardless of the tip
okay the waitress who treats all diners
the same regardless of the tip
and this is a specific quality
of buddha
as a refuge
they treat everybody the same no matter
how they treat the buddha
so they treat the buddha nice they treat
the buddha bad
they yell at you
they yell at you they praise you they
kick you they massage you
you treat them all the same okay so
there's another kind of equanimity
okay it's called uh
pentagon means to whether you have
done something for them lately or not
what's that joke
don't you remember i i gave you 100
bucks last year and then the answer is
well what do you done for me lately
you know and uh
buddhists don't have this question
buddhist don't say
yeah you ain't done nothing for me
lately you know so it's it's similar to
wag but different right
it's similar to the universal wagon lick
and then the idea that
even if she
she knows where's that waitress
i gotta find a bunch of waitresses it's
on my mind
i don't have one
i have a cafe and nobody in it
no customers and no stuff
right now it's equal uh but she
she's being nice to them
uh and she's not worried about it what
they do she's not gonna get tip or she's
not gonna get tipped she doesn't care
she's gonna treat you the same and
that's the last quality
of a buddha that we cover here okay
so i'm gonna go through the pictures one
more time
let's just go through them all right uh
for this
second class today we'll have three
classes today
let's review the pictures okay and then
we have a little extra time i'll give
you a preview of the next
first picture tip
starts with
it's the guy with the glasses at the
computer
somebody tell me when it's moved
yeah it's a it's a rhetorical question
huh i can't even
take care of myself and you want me to
take care of it
you must be joking okay
so that's the first thing to remember
from today's club
second one time
don't feel bad nobody else can help
anybody either
okay
so don't feel bad
every non
buddha
is in the same boat even up to arya's
even up to our hands
even up to people sitting out of the
boated tree but didn't get up yet
they're all in the same place you know
they look strong
but they are dead meat okay look strong
big meat okay they're not
guess what
nobody's better than you
to help everybody either
normal people can't help anybody either
even our yes even our hearts even people
recently mounted we can't really help
people
the total amount what next picture
what's that
is compared to
the help that
yeah nice the help that anyone who's not
a buddha yet could give to somebody is
this much
and the help that you can give to people
after your buddha is
equal to
equal to the
equal to the boundless universe
there's no comparison
one is infinite how do you compare
infinite to any number
all right and then we uh then he said
look uh
go back to the four things
that made buddhist
a worthy
object of refuge back in the refuge
teachings and then
reverse it and and feel good about
yourself because you're going to be
there
now now we're not talking taking refuge
we're talking
being directors yeah
and that has four quote quotes first one
was
totally fearless okay like
you will
nothing
can nothing can threaten you even death
cannot threaten
okay the ultimate threat is meaningless
for you you have overcome death itself
so you're like somebody's like i'm gonna
kill you like no you're not
chill out man i can't be killed
i'm i'm past that
okay so what else could worry you know
oh i'm gonna steal i'm gonna steal your
wallet
i have access numcodzi
i have access to the wealth of the
universe
like that
take the wallet okay god damn it you
know i have i'll i'll pick up 10 million
in
in the next five minutes you know
i'm i'm cool
take my wallet you know so imagine you
have this capacity okay
you'd be fearless
okay
next one tim
i like i mean focus on the word agile
and the idea of a super computer so you
are uh
[Music]
yeah
like uh
any problem people come to you with
you're like
oh yeah
they go like
okay but they saw you were gonna ask
before you asked
they knew the answer before you asked
okay that's convenient right but still
they do this again you know
oh let me figure it out you know oh i
got it you know okay
don't forget when you become a booty
after
it's a polite delay
you know oh
let me see
[Music]
they don't feel someone's closer or
someone's farther they feel everyone's
close
they never meet a person
who feels less intimate
or
or more or more
there's always
everyone feels the same to them
they love everyone
equal wag
okay
okay last one
and they don't care
what you do back to them they don't care
if you ever thank them
they don't care if you kick them
by the way when you get into this good
gooding business
you're going to get a good number of
kicks also
like save someone's life and then they
kick you and you're like okay
you know so this kind of uh
this kind of equanimity they they don't
care
if you
pay them back they don't care if you
praise them they don't care how you feel
about them they'll help you anyway
you know so they're just determined to
help you and that's a nice
way to live your life right like you
help people without any expectations
or even they hurt you back and you're
like yeah okay
here have some more money
here's some more
dharma and you know
so if we could reach that kind of uh
don't care what people
think about you just keep helping them
uh it's a very sweet place to be
you know yeah okay you hate my guns here
here's someone
yeah okay
okay
you messed up the cabin i cleaned up and
you that's cool
i'll still clean it for you
okay that it
okay and
uh
next we're going to talk more about
next class
about this attitude of
serving others
uh no matter what they do back to you
okay
all right guys etc
we'll see in the next
[Music]